I used to be a Malthusian.
كنت أعتقد في صحة كلام مالثيوس
This was my mental model of the world:
كان هذا نموذجي الذهني للعالم
exploding population, small planet;
إنفجار سكاني، وكوكب صغير
it's going to lead to ugly things.
سيقود الى أشياء قبيحة
But I'm moving past Malthus,
أنا أتخطى فكرة مالثيوس
because I think that we just might be about 150 years
لأنني أعتقد بأننا قد نكون على بُعد 150 عاماً
from a kind of new enlightenment.
من نوع جديد من التنوير
Here's why.
هذا هو السبب
This is the U.N.'s population data,
هذه بيانات إحصائية الأمم المتحدة للسكان
you may have seen, for the world.
ربما رأيتموها، للعالم
And the world's population expected to top out
ويتوقع أن يصل عدد سكان العالم الى أقصاه
at something hopefully a bit less than 10 billion, late this century.
نأمل في رقم أقل بقليل من 10 بلايين، نهاية هذا القرن
And after that, most likely it's going to begin to decline.
وبعد ذلك، من المرجح أنه سيبدأ بالتناقص
So what then?
اذا ماذا بعد؟
Most of the economic models are built around scarcity and growth.
معظم النماذج الإقتصادية مبنية على الندرة والنمو
So a lot of economists
لذا فالكثير من الإقتصاديين
look at declining population
ينظر لعدد السكان المتناقص
and expect to see stagnation, maybe depression.
ويتوقع أن يشهد ركود، ربما كساد
But a declining population is going to have
لكن عدد السكان المتناقص سيشهد
at least two very beneficial economic effects.
على الأقل أثنين من الآثار الإقتصادية المفيدة جداً
One: fewer people on a fixed amount of land
أولاً، سكان قليلون، في قطعة أرض محدودة
make investing in property a bad bet.
يجعل إستثمراهم في العقارات رهن سيئ
In the cities, a lot of the cost of property
في المدن، أكثر تكاليف الملكية
is actually wrapped up in its speculative value.
في الواقع مغطاة في قيمة مضاربتها
Take away land speculation,
بترك المضاربة في الأرض
price of land drops.
تنقص أسعار الأراضي
And that begins to lift a heavy burden
ويبدأ ذلك في إزاحة عبء ثقيل
off the world's poor.
عن فقراء العالم
Number two: a declining population
الشئ الثاني، تناقص عدد السكان
means scarce labor.
يعني ندرة الأيدي العاملة
Scarce labor drives wages.
ندرة الأيدي العاملة تزيد الأجور
As wages increase
بينما تزيد الأجور
that also lifts the burden on the poor and the working class.
هذا أيضاً يرفع العبء عن الفقراء والطبقة العاملة
Now I'm not talking about a radical drop in population like we saw in the Black Death.
الآن سأتحدث عن التناقص الحاد في السكان كما شهدنا في الموت الأسود
But look what happened in Europe
لكن أنظروا ما حدث في أوروبا
after the plague:
بعد الطاعون:
rising wages,
إرتفاع الأجور
land reform,
إصلاح الأراضي
technological innovation,
إبتكارات التكنلوجيا
birth of the middle class;
ميلاد الطبقة الوسطى
and after that, forward-looking social movements
وبعد ذلك، الحركات الإجتماعية تستشرف المستقبل
like the Renaissance,
مثل النهضة
and later the Enlightenment.
وبعدها التنوير
Most of our cultural heritage has tended to look backward,
معظم ثراثنا الثقافي يميل للنظر الى الوراء
romanticizing the past.
يحن الى الماضي
All of the Western religions begin with the notion of Eden,
معظم الديانات الغربية تبدأ مع فكرة عدن
and descend through a kind of profligate present
وتنحدر عبر هذا النوع من الحاضر المتهتك
to a very ugly future.
الى مستقبل قبيح جداً
So human history is viewed
اذا تاريخ البشرية نُظر له
as sort of this downhill slide
كنوع من هذا الإنزلاق الى أسفل
from the good old days.
من الأيام القديمة الجيدة
But I think we're in for another change,
لكني أعتقد أننا بصدد تغيير آخر
about two generations after the top of that curve,
بعد جيلين من قمة المنحنى
once the effects of a declining population
مجرد أن تبدأ تأثيرات تناقص السكان
start to settle in.
في الإستقرار
At that point, we'll start romanticizing the future again,
عند تلك النقطة، سنبدأ الحنين الى المستقبل مجدداً
instead of the nasty, brutish past.
بدلاً عن الماضي القذر، السيئ
So why does this matter?
اذا لماذا هذا مهم؟
Why talk about social-economic movements
لماذا الحديث عن الحراكات الإجتماعية الإقتصادية
that may be more than a century away?
التي ربما تبعد أكثر من قرن من الزمان؟
Because transitions are dangerous times.
لأن الأوقات الإنتقالية خطرة
When land owners start to lose money,
عندما يبدأ مُلاك الأرض في خسارة المال
and labor demands more pay,
ويطالب العمال بأجور أكثر
there are some powerful interests that are going to fear for the future.
هناك بعض المصالح القوية ستخاف من المستقبل
Fear for the future leads to some rash decisions.
الخوف من المستقبل يقود الى قرارات متهورة
If we have a positive view about the future
اذا كان لدينا نظرة إيجابية عن المستقبل
then we may be able to accelerate through that turn,
عندها ربما نقدر على تسريع تحقيق ذلك
instead of careening off a cliff.
بدلاً عن السقوط من المنحنى
If we can make it through the next 150 years,
اذا أستطعنا فعل ذلك خلال ال 150 عاماً القادمة
I think that your great great grandchildren
أعتقد أن أحفاد أحفاد أطفالنا
will forget all about Malthus.
سينسوا كل شئ عن مالثيوس
And instead, they'll be planning for the future
وبدلاً عنه، سيخططون للمستقبل
and starting to build the 22nd Century Enlightenment.
ويبدأوا في بناء تنوير القرن الثاني والعشرين
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)